I would like to recognize two individuals
if they are here. Scott Stornetta, are you
here? Been walking around. Is he in the
room? Samuel Smith. He took off. I was
hoping to, I want to acknowledge two
people whom I think are fathers of modern
digital trust. And I'll just say that
Scott Stornetta was cited by Satoshi
Nakamoto's Bitcoin paper. He's the
original conceiver of blockchain, which is
a really important innovation in digital
trust. We wouldn't have cryptocurrency
without that innovation. And literally the
creator of blockchain quoted Scott
Stornetta, who's been here today. He's out
in the hall or somewhere. And then Sam had
to leave. Sam is the creator of the KERI
protocol key event receipt infrastructure
that has inspired the SEDI identity model
including the very exciting thing I get to
talk about which is guardianship and
delegation. A really big breakthrough in
digital trust to solve a very thorny
problem. Now I'm going to break from how I
usually present things and I am going to
I'm
going to really almost read the slides
which I hate to do that but I know this is
being videoed And I know these
presentations are going to be asked for.
And I want anyone who gets this
presentation at a later time to be able to
understand every single point. And so
you're going to see me, you know,
basically reading some of this, but we're
going to go quickly. Really important
concept. First of all, a couple of
definitions. Guardianship gives someone
legal authority and responsibility to make
decisions for another, like a child or a
disabled person. So real key concepts
underlying there legal authority and
responsibility. Two different really
important concepts that make up
guardianship. Delegation, I want to wait
for my example to come up. There's a
little bit of a lag here. Temporarily
transfers specific duties or powers but
not full legal responsibility. Key
concepts are temporarily and specific
duties or powers and not full legal
responsibility. That's the difference
between guardianship and delegation. So
let's give an example. If a parent
delegates school pickup to a neighbor, the
parent still holds the ultimate
responsibility for the child's welfare.
Okay, that's just a task that has been
delegated, but not ultimate responsibility
or legal authority. Guardianship legally
transfers that responsibility. The
guardian and not the parent is now the one
accountable for decisions and care. So
those are the two conceptual differences.
Now I'm going to share with you 10 tools
that we use in combination to make
guardianship and delegation work as well
as all of the rest of the SEDI protocol. I
chose Lego here instead of a toolbox. The
difference is when you put Legos together,
you might make a pirate ship. You might
make a pirate, you might make spaceship,
you might make a dinosaur. You put them
together in different combinations to do
the thing you're trying to do. A toolbox,
you get out of the toolbox and you do
something to use the tools and then you're
done. So with SEDI, it's very much the
Legos, even though they are tools. The
first tool is verifiable containers. Now,
for those of you familiar with verifiable
credentials, we're talking about the same
concept, but a verifiable credential is
misnamed. It is a container that holds
data and makes it portable. It might or
might not be a credential. It can have
anything inside the container. It's the
container that's verifiable technically.
So it makes data portable and verifiable.
The next tool is secure attribution to
verify who digitally signed a thing. So if
you get a container that has some data in
it, who put that container together? Who
did it? And being able to secure part is
really important. Verify who did it. The
third tool, non-reputability. You can't
later say that you didn't. once it's been
signed, it is non-reputable. You can't
later say someone else did that. So when
you have encryption with TLS or HTTPS, you
see the encryption that happens on the
internet. There is repudiability. You
don't know who is on the other side of it.
It's not bound to a human person or an
individual. It's just there's a weak form
of authentication that goes with
encryption, but it's not like a digital
signature that you can actually bind to an
individual and say who did the thing.
Chain signatures which give you verifiable
provenance so you can actually see a chain
of authority rather than just a single
level. So if someone signs something like
a manager, well, who was their boss?
Where'd they get their authority from? Who
was their boss? Who did they work for? And
is that really the company? How do we know
that was really the company? And on you
can see a full chain and it's unlimited. A
full chain of provenance on there is
another really important tool. And then
weighted multisig critical for business
and on a whole lot of other cases we're
going to talk about here in a moment. But
weighted multisig means that you can have
one of two signatures. You can have one of
one, just one person signs it and they
have the full weight. You could have one
of two, two of three, five of seven, 11 of
92, whatever you make up. Okay. So it's
weighted because you can have one
signature have more weight than another.
and in a situation with divorced parents
and things like that and where the court
might be intervening, really important in
guardianship to have weighted multisig.
We'll talk a little bit about that.
Consent. The ability to use your identity
to make a non-reputable agreement and say,
I agree to a thing. Delegation of
authority, which we're going to talk about
in a little greater detail. Revocability
of that delegation. And critically, a
really important breakthrough with SEDI,
privacy respecting delegation. I was just
talking to a representative from another
state who said that the reason that they
were adopting a very popular technology
for identity is because their technical
people thought that there was no way to
get around a phone home for revocation.
That is not true. There is a way to get
around a phone home and have privacy
respecting revocation. Really important
breakthrough in digital trust in one of
the tools in SEDI. Graduated disclosure
which can be selective contractual.
Basically you can disclose as little as
you want to disclose when you're doing
something and there's actually a way to
only disclose that thing once terms for
disclosure have been agreed to and
consented to and that can happen behind
the scenes with agentic AI and these
agreements can be made and you actually
don't disclose a thing until the terms
have been agreed and it's mutual. It's
like a real-time NDA. done digitally.
Really exciting capability and detection
and recovery from compromise. As a matter
of fact, SEDI brings a four-step concept
I'm very excited about from a security
standpoint. SEDI expects compromise, then
it can detect compromise, then it can
contain compromise and recover. These are
mind-bendingly awesome in digital trust.
Expect, detect, contain, recover. Secure
attribution, really important in Utah law,
an electronic signature can be as legally
valid as handwritten with some
assumptions. There's got to be an intent
to sign. There's got to be attribution,
which is where SEDI comes in and really
helps consent to electronic transaction,
which interestingly, there's going to be a
dilemma, a legal one. Can you use digital
means to agree to use digital means?
That's going to be a fun one. And then no
legal exclusion. Sometimes there's a legal
exclusion that says you cannot use
digital. You must have paper. SEDI can use
its own tools to prove each of these.
Doesn't mean that we legally want it to.
There's going to be some policy debates,
but it does mean that SEDI can use the
tools to do these things. So guardianship,
examples of guardianship, parent of a
child, the natural guardian, guardian of a
disabled adult, guardian for an orphan,
orphan, which is court appointed or
temporary guardianship like when parents
are traveling. Guardianship is the missing
piece of government digital identity. You
don't see it anywhere. You don't see it
talked about. I think it is the cherry on
the Sunday when you're doing a digital
identity system if you're government. If
you're not government, you don't care as
much. But when you are government, you
absolutely are the dog wagged by the tail
of dependent populations. So these are the
children children, infants, elderly,
disabled, homeless, right? There's
advocates for all of those and they're
loud and they're powerful and they should
be. And so to be able to have guardianship
and digital guardianship that actually
brings those dependent populations into
the digital realm, really important stuff.
And if there's one takeaway from any
representatives of other states that are
looking at SEDI, there's some privacy and
autonomy reasons for looking at SEDI.
There's some security reasons for looking
at SEDI. But I think the number one reason
why a state would look at SEDI is because
of digital guardianship. Because it
includes everybody. All the different
dependent populations you want to include.
No government system has figured this out.
Few of them are even talking about it.
Only 25% of US 16 year olds get a driver's
license. Only 50% of 20 year olds have
driver's licenses. But yet 100% of 15teen
-year-olds need identity.
SETI solves a big technical challenge,
decentralized digital guardianship that's
peer-to-peer with no phone home and no
dependence on any vendor network or
blockchain. That's a really important
thing. You know what's easy to do
technically? To prove a guardian
relationship, if you phone home to a
server and the server says, oh yeah,
that's the parent of the child, we're
good. And you're phoning home to the
server. That's easy technically to do. You
know it's extremely hard that requires the
breakthroughs enabled by Sam Smith, who I
mentioned earlier, is to be able to verify
that guardian relationship in a
decentralized manner where you're not
phoning home. Offline, using Bluetooth
peer-to-peer, major breakthrough in
digital trust. Now, you know, I gave these
guys some kudos at the beginning. SEDI can
mimic any form of guardianship. A guardian
can prove that the guardian award can
prove who their guardian is and verifiers
can follow guardian requirements for award
authorization. So what I mean by that is
Johnny requests to spend 35 bucks on
Fortnite and his mother is prompted for
approval. It's a simple example of how a
verifier can follow guardian requirements
for award authorization. Guardianship
however gets very tricky. A single
guardian is very simple. It's one-to-one.
A single parent actually is the simplest
use case. A single parent just they're the
only one who makes the decision, right? It
gets trickier when there's two parents.
When they're married, it's still trickier
than a single single because you can say
the parents either one of them can say
Johnny can do it. You can say both of them
have to approve before Johnny can do it.
You can say up to a certain dollar amount
either parent can do it, but if it exceeds
another dollar amount, then both parents
need to be able to do it. and that's what
I call graduated. So you can have
conditions in there and things like that
for that approval. It gets even trickier
with divorced parents where you have a two
-to-one relationship with Johnny,
potentially a three-to-one relationship if
the court is involved, which they might be
for some things that Johnny might want to
do. And there's waiting. So you can give
more weight to the court. You can give
more weight to one parent. You can give
weight to a grandparent. You can do
whatever you want. It's called weighted M
of N multi-sig and so you can divide that
authority however you choose. And adults
show children of a disabled parent. So
I've got a mother who's 89 and she's
starting to forget some things and she's
got a lot of living adult children. And
there's some of these adult children who
should probably not have a say in what
happens with mom. It's an opinion, but at
some point that might have to be
adjudicated. And someone might have to
say, well, when push comes to sub, the
kids are not agreeing. How is that
adjudicated? And however that is, if the
conclusion is that a certain subset of
children have authority and maybe one has
more than the others, that can be modeled
with MFN weighted multisig, which is part
of KERI, part of SEDI. How about homeless
people unable to carry credentials? Well,
what are you doing there to bring that
homeless person in the digital realm if
they're unable to carry credentials? How
does work in real life. We try to mimic
what happens in real life and that is
there's a government agency that actually
holds some credentials or has the ability
to do something on behalf of that homeless
person. Very tricky situations. And I'm
going a little bit slower than I want so
I'm going to go a lot faster. Delegation.
A parent signs a permission slip that
authorizes another adult child to pick up
their child or a manager delegates a task
or an individual delegates to an AI agent.
We talk about AI and agentic AI. That is a
form of delegation. Delegation is
absolutely everywhere. A legislature can
delegate to committees and agencies who
then delegate to departments and outside
companies who delegate multiple levels of
employees who provide a service to a
citizen. So delegation is absolutely
everywhere. All organizations, private or
public or are hierarchies of delegation.
SEDI enables an individual to directly
delegate authority to another without
involving anyone else. else. The
individual, the authority can go directly
to the delegate and give them that
authority. With SEDI anyone anywhere can
verify the claimed authority without
phoning home. We talked about that earlier
decentralization. SEDI can mimic any form
of delegation. A delegator can prove what
and to whom they've delegated. A delegate
can prove what's delegated and from whom.
And by the way, the word delegate a little
bit awkward because in some cases a noun,
in some cases a verb. Okay, so I'm I'm
using the form delegate here in number
two. A delegate noun can prove what's
delegated verb and from home. Delegation
can expire or be revoked. A delegate can
delegate again with proof of authority to
do so. Delegations are non-reputable which
means they can't be denied later.
Delegations can form hierarchies or
chains. They're auditable, traceable. They
cannot be forged. They're resilient to key
rotation. And rules and restrictions can
be made verifiable, machine readable, and
enforceable. Sounds like a dream list. It
is. Now you know why we're excited.
Agentic future, by the way, I have to
laugh at this picture of grandma being
helped by a robot. And no, that wasn't
made by AI. And no, I didn't take that
photo. But Microsoft CEO said this and I'm
paraphrasing because this quote is too
long, but the the paraphrase of the
Microsoft CEO, AI agents will replace all
software as a service, SaaS. class. CEO of
Microsoft. And the reason he says that is
because of frankly what I think is
illustrated by grandma. It's a user
experience. Most agentic tasks are simple
and don't require delegation, but some
important ones do. And they require some
delegation, some authority on behalf of
the agent. And I think one of the greatest
use cases, I keep it in the wrong button
and gets rid of them. I think one of the
greatest use cases for agentic AI is user
experience for elderly people. I know my
mom could talk to an agent and ask her to
do something. She struggles to open her
phone and start an app to play Scrabble
with her daughter in Pennsylvania. But I
know she could talk to an agent and say,
please open the Scrabble game or please do
something. I think the future of AI for
elderly people is really, really bright.
And I want that agent's authority to do
something on behalf of my mom, carefully
constrained.
SEDI is ideal for delegating to agentic
AI. So in conclusion, SEDI brings
guardianship and delegation into
verifiable digital form, harmonizing law
and technology. SEDI includes everyone
through digital guardianship. Parents,
caregivers, and courts can securely
represent those who cannot self-manage
their identity. Through SEDI, delegation
individuals can safely empower others or
AI agents with limited revocable
authority. SETI actualizes both human and
legal rights and principles and is
designed for the coming agentic AI era.
Thank you.